A Guide to the Langston Hughes Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8870-e
Langston Hughes Collection 1925-1956
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8870-e
11 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase 1992 September 2
Item Listing
- Letters
  - Langston Hughes, Westfield, New Jersey, to [Henry Lee] Moon, [1930] May 1; ALS, 1 p.
    [Unable to write an article for the Tuskegee Messenger because "my novel and earning a living have kept me bowed down for the last three years"; says his next novel,
    Not Without Laughter
    , will be published in August and "it's not about Harlem"; encloses poem "Alabama Earth (At Booker Washington's grave)".]
  - Langston Hughes, Washington, D. C. (postcard of colorized photograph of the Lincoln Memorial), to Henry Lee Moon, Tuskegee Institute, Alabama, 1930 June 8; APCS
    [Advises Moon to leave the poem ("Alabama Earth") "as is, please, sir!"; mutual friends Alain Locke and Zora Neale Hurston are mentioned.]
  - Langston Hughes, New York, New York (colorized postcard "On the Beach at Rockaway Beach"), to Henry Lee Moon, Tuskegee Institute, Alabama, 1930 July 18; APCS
    [Thanks Moon for sending copies of the Tuskegee Messenger; mentions Zora Neale Hurston and his mother [ Carrie Langston Hughes]; says " New York's full of down home teachers at school" and hopes "the novel [
    ?] don't bore you."]
  - Langston Hughes, "On tour/Columbia, N[orth] C[arolina] (on stylized personal stationery "LH")," to [Henry Lee] Moon, 1931 Nov 21; ALS, 2 p.
    [lengthy and detailed recounting of his speaking at Chapel Hill, social arrangements in segregated North Carolina("Refreshments later at a white soda fountain.... Nothing happened. It was just like New York."); mentions
    Contempo
    magazine, describes his reading before a large audience whom he expected would be hostile but were not (a policeman stood guard outside the building) after controversy surrounding his "Nigger Christ" poem ("Christ In Alabama", which commented on the Scottsboro case and was published in
    ); Hughes quotes a local sheriff as saying "he doesn't mind Christ being a bastard, but don't call him a nigger!". In a lengthy section marked "Not For Publication" Hughes describes two parties given in his honor (one hosted by Andrew Mellon's nephew) for after the reading where "Southern ladies present, too... gallons of home-brew were consumed" and adds that the tour is going well and plans to visit Birmingham. ]
  - Langston Hughes, Cleveland, Ohio, to [Henry Lee] Moon, 1936 March 25; ALS, 1 p.
    [World premiere of his play
    Little Ham
    , which Hughes missed due to illness; thanks Moon for sending some papers and asks, "How come you can't buy an Amsterdam News nowhere in this town?" Also mentions illness of his mother.]
  - Langston Hughes, Cleveland, to Henry Lee Moon, New York, New York, 1936 July 22; TLS, 1 p.
    [Sends a clipping [not present] and says " Etta Motten's description of Rio makes me want to go down there right away. Cleveland is just the same as ever, but I am glad to be back home and back to work again."]
  - Langston Hughes, New York, New York (on personalized stationery, with envelope), to Molly and Henry Lee Moon, 1955 Nov 28; TLS, 1 p.
    [Invites the Moons to his home on December 10 to meet "the distinguished South African writer of colour, Peter Abrahams... I find Mr. Abrahams a charming fellow and a most interesting conversationalist"; in a handwritten postscript (green ink) Hughes adds, "Not a party--just a salon!"]
  - Langston Hughes, New York, (on personalized stationery, with envelope), to Henry Lee Moon, 1956 Oct 20; TLS, 1 p.
    [Advance copies of
    I Wonder As I Wander
    are "due at any moment" and Moon will receive a copy from the publisher
    Pictorial History of The Negro In America
    will appear November 18 "and we're all delighted Mollie [Moon's wife Molly] is helping on it. Crown [Publishers] finds her charming."]
- Manuscripts
  - Langston Hughes poem "Alabama Earth (At Booker Washington's grave)", [1930 May 1]; Tmss, 1 p.
    [This signed copy was originally enclosed with a Hughes letter to Henry Lee Moon, May 1, 1930.]
  - Langston Hughes poem "Cross", 12 lines, [1925]; Amss, 1 p.
    [Describes the emotions of the child of a white father and a black mother; at the bottom of the page Hughes has written, "On this poem my play Mulatto is based."]
- Printed
  - Sheet music, Checkin' On The Freedom Train, lyrics by Langston Hughes and music by Sammy Heyward, published by Handy Brothers Music Co., Inc., Broadway, New York, 1947; Printed, 12 p.
    [Based on Hughes' 1947 poem
    Ballad of The Freedom Train
    , published in
    The New Republic
    (September 1947): 27.]